

Tiago Filipe Sousa Gonçalves

- Porto, Portugal
- +351 914531059
- ☑ tiago.galves@hotmail.com | tiago.gonalves@gmail.com
- ★ https://tiagofilipesousagoncalves.github.io
- in https://www.linkedin.com/in/tiagofilipegoncalves/
- https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4744-9174

I received my MSc in Bioengineering (Biomedical Engineering) from Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto (FEUP) in 2019. Currently, I am a PhD Candidate in Electrical and Computer Engineering at FEUP and a research assistant at the Centre for Telecommunications and Multimedia of INESC TEC with the Visual Computing & Machine Intelligence (VCMI) Research Group. My research interests include machine learning, explainable artificial intelligence (in-model approaches), computer vision, medical decision support systems, and machine learning deployment.

Besides working, I enjoy practising Karate-Do Shotokai or reading about life, philosophy, economy, politics or fundamental science. Moreover, I do not refuse a good TV series or a good film (preferably at the cinema).

Experience

2021 - Present

Invited Teaching Assistant

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

- Invited Teaching Assistant during the 1st Semester of 2022-2023 on the course PRO Programming (L.EEC004)
- Invited Teaching Assistant during the 1st Semester of 2021-2022 on the course TAIA
 Advanced Topics on Artificial Intelligence

2020 - Present

Research Assistant

INESC TEC | Centre for Telecommunications and Multimedia

2019 - 2020

Research Assistant

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

2018 - 2018

Junior Researcher

Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS

Education

2020 – Present

Doctor of Philosophy Electrical and Computer Engineering

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

 Thesis Title: "Interpretable Machine Learning and its Application to Medical Decision Support Systems"

2016 - 2019

Bachelor of Science & Master of Science Bioengineering – Biomedical Engineering

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

• Thesis Title: "Deep Aesthetic Assessment of Breast Cancer Surgery Outcomes"

2013 - 2016

Bachelor of Science

Bioengineering – Biomedical Engineering

Faculty of Biotechnology | Universidade Católica Portuguesa

Awards

2021 MICCAI Hackathon 2021 Best Contribution Award

 Member of the winning team "HIT" (Helena Montenegro, Isabel Rio-Torto, João Nunes and Tiago Gonçalves) with the work titled "Show Me Consistency! Increasing the quality and consistency of annotations"

2021 2nd Place World Data League

 Member of the team "Tech Moguls" (Joana Morgado, Paulo Maia, Tiago Gonçalves and Tomé Albuquerque) that achieved 2nd place at the World Data League competition on data science

Extracurricular Activities

2021 - 2022 VISion Understanding and Machine intelligence (VISUM) Summer School 2022

- Leader of the Project Committee
- · Member of the Organising Committee

2021 – 2022 2nd Workshop on Explainable & Interpretable Artificial Intelligence for Biometrics at WACV 2022

- · Member of the Organising Committee
- · Sponsorship Co-chair

2020 - 2021 VISion Understanding and Machine intelligence (VISUM) Summer School 2021

- Member of the Organising Committee
- · Member of the Project Committee

2020 – 2021 1st Workshop on Explainable & Interpretable Artificial Intelligence for Biometrics at WACV 2021

- Member of the Organising Committee
- · Sponsorship Co-chair

2019 - 2020 VISion Understanding and Machine intelligence (VISUM) Summer School 2020

· Member of the Organising Committee

2020 – 2021 Conselho Nacional de Debates Universitários (Portuguese Universities Debating Council)

Treasurer of the Board of Directors

2019 – 2021 Sociedade de Debates da Universidade do Porto (University of Porto Debate Society)

- President of the Audit Committee
- Treasurer of the Board of Directors

2017 – 2019 Associação Nacional de Estudantes de Engenharia Biomédica (Portuguese Biomedical Engineering Students' Association)

- · Treasurer of the Board of Directors
- Founder and Secretary of the General Assembly

2017 - Present European Students, Sustainability Auditing (ESSA Project)

· Social Responsibility Student Auditor

2017 - 2019 ShARE-UP

- · President of the Board of Directors
- Network Manager of the Energy Network

2016 – 2017 **Uniplaces** • Uniplaces Academy - Ambassador Program · University Partnerships Manager Porto · Creative & Social Media Manager Porto Núcleo de Estudantes de Bioengenharia FEUP/ICBAS 2016 - 2018 (Bioengineering Student Association FEUP/ICBAS) • Member of the Communication and Image Department Associação de Estudantes da Escola Superior de Biotecnologia 2013 - 2016 (Student's Union of the Faculty of Biotechnology) · Treasurer of the Board of Directors · Vice-President of the Board of Directors Sociedade de Debates da Católica Porto 2013 - 2016 (Católica Porto Debate Society) • President of the Audit Committee · Founder and President of the Board of Directors 2013 - 2021 Tuna da Universidade Católica Portuguesa – Porto (Academic Band of Universidade Católica Portuguesa – Porto) · President of the Audit Committee · Vice-President of the General Assembly · Vice-President of the Board of Directors Vice-President of the Audit Committee Erasmus+ Buddy (Faculty of Biotechnology) 2015 - 2016 • Member of the Erasmus+ Buddy Committee Clube de Investigadores – Escola Superior de Biotecnologia 2013 - 2014 (Researchers Club – Faculty of Biotechnology) · Project "Bacteria around the City", under the supervision of Professor Célia Manaia Programa de Mentorado – Escola Superior de Biotecnologia 2013 - 2016 (Mentorship Programme – Faculty of Biotechnology) • Mentorship Programme under the supervision of the Alumnus José Carlos Pereira Jornadas de Biotecnologia - Escola Superior de Biotecnologia 2014 - 2015 (Journeys of Biotechnology – Faculty of Biotechnology) · Treasurer of the Organising Committee • BSc Representative of the Organising Committee **Technical Skills Programming Languages** • Python MATLAB JavaScript • C/C++ HTML · CSS **Programming Frameworks** Bootstrap Wordpress Django **Technologies** Docker Personal Skills

Languages Known

- Portuguese: Reading (Native), Writing (Native), Speaking (Native)
- English: Reading (Excellent), Writing (Excellent), Speaking (Excellent)
- French: Reading (Intermediate), Writing (Intermediate), Speaking (Intermediate)
- · Spanish: Reading (Fair), Writing (Fair), Speaking (Fair)

Strengths

- Leadership
- Team management
- Ability to self-manage
- Variety of team members
- Personal motivation
- Personal communication
- Teamwork
- Adaptability
- Networking
- · Online marketing
- · Creative thinking
- · Social media management
- Brand awareness
- Distance work
- Writing
- · Public speaking

Interests

- · Biomedical Engineering
- Machine Learning
- · Deep Learning
- Artificial Intelligence
- · Biomedical Image Processing & Analysis
- Music
- Martial Arts (Karate Do Shotokai)
- Volunteering
- Literature
- Politics
- Entrepreneurship

Publications

International Conference and Journal Articles

- 1. Tiago Gonçalves, Isabel Rio-Torto, Luís F. Teixeira, and Jaime S. Cardoso. A survey on attention mechanisms for medical applications: are we moving toward better algorithms? *IEEE Access*, 10:98909–98935, 2022
- 2. Pedro C. Neto, Tiago Gonçalves, Marco Huber, Naser Damer, Ana F. Sequeira, and Jaime S. Cardoso. Orthomad: Morphing attack detection through orthogonal identity disentanglement. In 2022 International Conference of the Biometrics Special Interest Group (BIOSIG), pages 1–5, 2022
- 3. Ana F Sequeira, Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, João Ribeiro Pinto, and Jaime S Cardoso. An exploratory study of interpretability for face presentation attack detection. *IET Biometrics*, 10(4):441–455, 2021
- 4. João Ribeiro Pinto, Tiago Gonçalves, Carolina Pinto, Luís Sanhudo, Joaquim Fonseca, Filipe Gonçalves, Pedro Carvalho, and Jaime S Cardoso. Audiovisual classification of group emotion valence using activity recognition networks. In 2020 IEEE 4th International Conference on Image Processing, Applications and Systems (IPAS), pages 114–119. IEEE, 2020
- 5. Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, Maria J Cardoso, and Jaime S Cardoso. Deep image segmentation for breast keypoint detection. In *Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute Proceedings*, volume 54, page 35, 2020
- Sara P Oliveira, João Ribeiro Pinto, Tiago Gonçalves, Rita Canas-Marques, Maria-João Cardoso, Hélder P Oliveira, and Jaime S Cardoso. Weakly-supervised classification of her2 expression in breast cancer haematoxylin and eosin stained slides. *Applied Sciences*, 10(14):4728, 2020
- 7. Ana F Sequeira, Wilson Silva, João Ribeiro Pinto, Tiago Gonçalves, and Jaime S Cardoso. Interpretable biometrics: Should we rethink how presentation attack detection is evaluated? In 2020 8th International Workshop on Biometrics and Forensics (IWBF), pages 1–6. IEEE, 2020
- 8. Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, Maria J Cardoso, and Jaime S Cardoso. A novel approach to keypoint detection for the aesthetic evaluation of breast cancer surgery outcomes. *Health and Technology*, pages 1–13, 2020
- 9. Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, and Jaime Cardoso. Deep aesthetic assessment of breast cancer surgery outcomes. In *Mediterranean Conference on Medical and Biological Engineering and Computing*, pages 1967–1983. Springer, 2019